Guide to the Esther M. Lederberg papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
- Additional material, Accession ARCH-2008-047
  - Tn and IS allocations (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Nobel Prize Ceremony photographs (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Various photographs (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Loose photographs (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Various loose photos (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Loose photos; obituaries for E. Lederberg (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - PRC materials (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Soffer papers (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Japanese correspondence (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Adler correspondence (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Envelope of unsorted snapshots (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Envelope of unsorted snapshots (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence "A" (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence "B" (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence "C" (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence "D" (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence "E" (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence "F" (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Personal Correspondence "G" (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Personal Correspondence "H" (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Personal Correspondence "I" (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Personal Correspondence "J" (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Personal Correspondence "K" (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Personal Correspondence "L" (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Personal Correspondence "M" (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Personal Correspondence "N" (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Personal Correspondence "O" (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Personal Correspondence "P" (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Personal Correspondence "Q" (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Personal Correspondence "R" (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Personal Correspondence "S" (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Personal Correspondence "T" (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Personal Correspondence "UV" (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence "W" (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence "XYZ" (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Huberman, Joel – Letter and Photographs (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "Biagi, Gino, and EML" in Venice - Photograph (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Alexander, Ellen, Memorial Service (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Simon, Matthew letter to Fraser, Kevin (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Simon, Matthew (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - "Perspectives: Anecdotal, Historical, and Critical Commentaries on Genetics" – James F. Crow (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - The Plasmid Song (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Papers by Esther Lederberg, 1944, 1952, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Papers by Esther Lederberg, 1955, 1978, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Seven reprints/articles by others, 1968-74 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Kalckar/Yarmolinsky correspondence, 1961-72 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Reprints of papers, some by Lederberg (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - 1988 Schedule (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - "The Dynamic Genome" Book Review (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Microbial Genetics Bulletins, 1950, 1971, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Lederberg, Esther, correspondence, mostly 1961 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Reprinted articles, including "Perspectives" (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Beadle, George W. Papers (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Luria, Salvador Obituary (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Lecture Notes for Esther Lederberg from 1969 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - General Notes from Esther Lederberg (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Publications List for Esther Lederberg (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Article concerning re-appointment to board of trustees (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - "Uniform Nomenclature for Bacterial Plasmids" 1976 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Misc. information about PRC (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Excerpts from "A Short History or Molecular Biology" by Max Planck Institute (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Russian Interview with Esther Lederberg, Bombay, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Obituary of Gunther Stent (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Letters from Oparin, A.I. (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Russian version of Esther Lederberg - Wikipedia article (Box 13, Folder 14)
- Additional material, Accession ARCH-2009-152
  - Correspondence and papers used in constructing the website: The Esther M. Zimmer Lederberg Memorial Web Site [DQ] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notebook from BRL sequencing course (using phi X174 in an experiment), August 1980 [DH] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Genetic Stocks of Bacteria and Bacterial Viruses, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, 1968 [DL] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - International Genetics Symposium to Honor James F. Crow, University of Wisconsin, Madison, June 1986 [DL] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of EL and others (includes one titled “Serious Young Esther) [DL] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Obituary for Rebecca Hart Anderson 1995; Memorial Service note for Saralinda Alexander Rhodes, 2001 [DL] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Einstein, Elizabeth, note to EL written on reply card to sympathy notes for death of Hans Einstein, 1973 [DL] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Plasmid Reference Center materials (mostly correspondence) 1977-83 [DL] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Plasmid Reference Center nomenclature (mostly correspondence) 1977-81 [DL] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Salmonella notes and correspondence, 1970-74 [DD] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Salmonella research and correspondence, 1967-73 [DE] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Nomenclature of Transposable Elements in Prokaryotes, Gene, 5 (1979) 197-206 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lysate photographs (includes paper by Calef and Guerrini “Studies on Gal Deletions in e.coli K12”) ca. 1962 [DF] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Third Annual Symposium of Antibiotic Resistance, correspondence (Vladimir Krcmery, E. Garfield, EMZL) re, 1975-76 [DG] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Class notebook: Botany 128 Cytogenetics, UC Berkeley, 1947 [DI.A] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Class paper: Bacteriology 250, UC Berkeley, 1946 [DI.B] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Class material: Ag. Bacteriology 131, 1948 [DI.B] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Notes: microbial genetics, 1954 [DI.B] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Class notes: Bacteriology 108, UC Berkeley, 1950 [DI.C] (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Class notebook: Biochemistry 105, U Wisconsin, 1947-48 [DI.D] (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Class notebook: Calculus, U Wisconsin, 1952 [DI.E] (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Class notebook: Ag. Bacteriology 128, U Wisconsin, 1949 [DI.F] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Class notebook: Ag. Bacteriology 127 (Industrial Bacteriology), U Wisconsin, 1948-49 [DI.G] (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Class material: Ag. Biochemistry 208, U Wisconsin, 1956-57 [DI.H] (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Class notebook: Agronomy 136 Biometry, U Wisconsin, 1949 [DI.I] (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Personal correspondence (Alex & Pam Reiser and others), 1994-2003 [DM] (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Photograph of Stanford campus with note from Esther to parents on her arrival at Stanford, Sept. 23, 1944 [DJ] (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Miscellany: Pocket Opera 2009 program; Microbiological Reviews 51 (4) December 1987; and correspondence re use of photo of EMZL in an exhibit [DJ] (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Reprints – E. Lederberg [DJ] (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Reprints – J. Lederberg [DJ] (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Reprints – other authors [DJ] (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - PRC handouts, 1979-80 [DJ] (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Christensen, Clyde M. Keys to the Common Fleshy Fungi, Burgess Publishing, 1946 [DN] (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Movable Genetic Elements; abstracts of papers presented at the XLV Cold Spring Harbor Symposium on Quantitative Biology, 1980 [DO] (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Mortelmans, Kristien Emannuela, “Effect of R Plasmids on Salmonella Typhimurium…” dissertation, Stanford University, 1975 [DP] (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Slides for talks #1 [DK] (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Slides for talks #2 [DK] (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Slides for talks #3 [DK] (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Photographs [DK] (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Negatives (in film can) [DK] (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Photo Album 1959-61: house, Povar, Tetsuo lino (Box 2)
  - Photo Album 1961-62: lab, Japan, Daniel Mazia (Box 2)
  - Photo Album 1962: Walter Bodmer, Tetsuo lino, Mari Wright, Esther playing recorder, two clippings [+ 5 folders of loose photos, clippings from the album] (Box 2)
  - Photo Album Summer 1965-September 1966: JL and EML family photos, AT Ganesan, Rockefeller U., Judy Forshman; Gunther Stent, Inge Stent, S. Brenner, at Kappadoci (Pacific Coast house) (Box 2)
  - Photo Album 1967: music, unidentified persons in lab (Box 2)
  - Photo Album 1968: parents; music groups including Phil Hand, Dave Berry; Dorothy Carroll (MPRO); other unidentified musicians (Box 2)
  - Folder: family photos removed from undated album (Box 2)
  - Folder: clipping on EL removed from undated album (Box 2)
  - Accordion file of photos: EML at Munich Conference, 1978; Hans Semelson; X Int’l Congress of Microbiology; EML and MLS at his apartment; Newell and Mary Ellen Ford; A. Campbell; Mission Santa Barbara Music Festival; Jane Stocker and daughters; Norton Zinder; Roy Curtiss III, Lou Barron and Ken Timmis (Box 2)
  - Esther M. Zimmer, “Mutant Strains of Neurospora Deficient in Para-aminobenzoic Acid,” Stanford MA thesis, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Pasteur Award (The Society of Illinois Bacteriologists, Inc.) presented to Joshua and Esther M. Lederberg, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Dernham [Postdoctural Fellowship] Award certificate 1969 (Box 2)
- Additional material, Accession ARCH-2010-011
  - Photo album [DR], 1980 (Box 1)
  - Photo album [DS], 1946-1950 (Box 1)
  - Photo album [DT], 1946-1950 (Box 1)
  - Photo album, Cold Spring Harbor [DU], undated (Box 1)
  - Photo album, conferences at CIBA (London) and The Burn (Scotland) [DV], 1956 (Box 1)
  - Photo album, conference at Royaumont [DW], 1958 (Box 1)
  - Photo album, people from Stanford laboratories, many taken at 716 Alvarado Row [DX], 1968 (Box 1)
  - Photo album: people playing music, lab party at the beach, researchers at 716 Alvarado Row, party for Masatoshi Enamoto, Sandor Salgo, Ellen Alexander family [EB], 1970-1972 and undated (Box 2)
  - Photo album: Mario Duchesne, party at 716 with colleagues, Jim Crow, Walter Bodmer, Galen Bradley [EC], 1969-70 (Box 2)
  - Photo album: Bruce Stocker and other colleagues, Walter Bodmer, relatives [ED], 1972-73 (Box 2)
  - Photo album: Stan Cohen’s 60th birthday celebration at Silverado [EE] (Box 2)
  - Folder [EG] containing family photographs; photos of Sam Anderson and others at the Stanford “Bio Patio”, ca. 1945, M. M. Rhoades, Jim Crow, and Josh; and a fragment of Esther’s parents’ wedding invitation (Box 2)
  - Envelope of photo negatives [EH] (Box 2)
  - Hunter College bachelor’s diploma, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Stanford Master of Science diploma, 1946 (Box 2)
  - University of Wisconsin, PhD diploma, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Articles, etc, related to Esther’s interest in Charles Dickens (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Articles, etc, related to Esther’s interest in Charles Dickens (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Assorted reprints and publications, including an email from Christine Mortelmans with biographical article on Joshua Lederberg with reference to Esther (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and professional papers: includes statement of availability, War Manpower Commission, 1944; letter from Donald Kennedy on her 25th anniversary at Stanford, 1985; and letter from EZL to Mr. and Mrs. Sargeant Schriver, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - David Zimmer documents (birth certificate and elementary school report cards from Sereth), 1906-1911 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Family documents (Esther’s birth certificate, 1922; invitation to wedding of Pauline Geller and David Zimmer, 1920; map and several letters pertaining to burial plots on Staten Island, 1957-63 and undated) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letters of recommendation for EZL (includes Arthur Kornberg, Allan Campbell, Edward Tatum, H. G. duBuy, H. F Fraser, and Alvin J. Clarke), 1944, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Names and addresses (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Notes on using lab computer (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Plasmid Database Project: notes and documentation, including a manual written by Bart Anderson, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Program from Stanford Commencement, with EZL’s annotations, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Web printouts of German articles with reference to Esther, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Additional material, Accession ARCH.2012-029
      - Lysocenicity of Escherichia Coli Strain K-12 (typescript) (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Biographical correspondence and photographs (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional material, Accession ARCH-2010-110
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence A-C, 1942-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence D-J, 1944-1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence K-O, 1947-1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence P-Z, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence Misc., 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence A-H, 1948-1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence K-P, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence R-Z, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence A-Z, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence A-C, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence D-M, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence P-Z, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, unsorted, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence A-C, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence D-J, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence K-P, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence R-Z, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence A-D, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Corrrespondence E-L, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correpondence M-Z, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence A-C, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence D-J, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence K-M, 1962-1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence N-R, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence S-Z, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence: Maurice Atkinson, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence A-B, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence D-G, 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence J-P, 1967-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence S-Z, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence ("Trip letters"), 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: Jennifer Angel, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence A-G, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence H-N, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence P-W, 1969-1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, Misc., 1971 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence A-C, 1973-1976 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence D-G, 1972-1976 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence Misc., 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence H-L, 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence M-P, 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: Platt, John, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence R-T, 1974-1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence W-Z, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Additional cards, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Misc. materials re Esther Lederberg memorial website (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Additional material, Accession ARCH.2013-031
  - Edward A Adelberg, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Raymond Appleyard, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - R.K. Bretthauer, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Victor Bruce, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chernoff, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Enrico [Calef?], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Allan Campbell, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Amylou Collins, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dr S.T. Cowan, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - [Max?] Delbruck, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bruce Holloway, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ernest B. Hook, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Francois Jacob, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dale Kaiser, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Joshua Lederberg, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Margaret (Peggy) Lieb, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Frank Mukai, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Aaron [Novick?], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - J.C. Sherris, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - T.M. Sonneborn, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bruce Stocker, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - J Weigle, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bernard Weisblum, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Leslie Williams, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Elie Wollman, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - C. Yanofsky, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Index to Letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Nobel Ceremony photographs, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Plasmid Reference Center- Technical Proposal, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bacteria Articles, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Reprints, Bibliographies, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "A Genetic Ode" poem, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Patterns of Discovery" Seminar at UC Berkeley, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Articles, clippings by Joshua Lederberg, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1966-1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Holiday Correspondence, 1959-2003 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Esther Lederberg - Elementary School report cards, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Birth & Marriage Certificates - Joshua and Esther Lederberg, David Zimmer, Pauline Geller, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Esther M. Lederberg, Memorial Resolution, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Event Programs, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Website [http://esthermlederberg.com/], 2010-2013; Accession ARCH-2014-139; 17408 megabyte(s) (101,253 files in 3,809 Folders)